Guide to the Wednesday Music Club records CBHM.0013
Center for Brooklyn History
Wednesday Music Club records
1946-2022
Center for Brooklyn History
Wednesday Music Club
CBHM.0013
1 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes
This collection documents the activities of the Wednesday Music Club and includes minutes, programs, correspondence, constitution, bylaws, photographs, and clippings.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Wednesday Music Club, 1990. An addition to the collection was deposited by the club's Board of Directors in 2022. The materials constituting the addition had been collected by Harriet Wohlgemuth and left to the Board.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type under the original folder headings. Within each folder, the materials are arranged chronologically, except for the performer materials which are arranged alphabetically by surname.
Historical note
The Wednesday Music Club was established in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1882 as the Schumann Club, an invitation-only membership organization. The club's original membership was comprised of female pianists who would meet to play the music of Robert Schumann. In the 1920s the club's name was changed to the Wednesday Music Club so that its members could play the work of other composers. As of 2022, the Wednesday Music Club still meets in Brooklyn Heights for several annual events.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Civitas Club collection (ARC.300)
Mrs. Field's Literary Club records (1995.004)
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006): Roosa School of Music
Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272): Entertainment -- Bargemusic
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities of the Wednesday Music Club and includes minutes, programs, correspondence, constituion, bylaws, photographs, and clippings spanning the period 1946 to 2022.
Music publishing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Music |x Societies, etc.; Minutes; Clippings (information artifacts); Constitutions; Bylaws (administrative records); Wednesday Music Club
- Minutes, 1946-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  Scope and Contents
  These minutes are handwritten into three notebooks which also have flyers, programs, rosters, and other material either taped onto or tucked between the pages. Some of these materials are duplicated in other folders in this collection.
- Correspondence, rosters, club histories, circa 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Club programs, 1967-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Some of these are duplicated elsewhere in the collection.
- Programs, 1960s-2020s (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  Some of these are duplicated in the minute books.
- Performer bios, circa 1980s-2020s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes correspondence and ephemera related to the performers.
- Constitution, by-laws, and history, circa 1987-2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Financial, 1986-2017 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Member directories and rosters, 1967-2017 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Letters from president, 1975-2017 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- [Logo], 2012 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Meeting minutes and membership info, 1982-2018 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Committees, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Press, 1961-2009 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photos, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Set of 4 x 6 color photographs of a house concert.
- Invitations, 2006-2016 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Harriet [Wohlgemuth] bio and photos, circa 1978-2010s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes programs from Wohlgemuth's performances outside of the club.
- In memoriam, 2006-2016 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Programs, clippings, and correspondence relating to club members who passed away.